Georgetown, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1731-1866.
Congregational Library Archives
Georgetown, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1731-1866.
RG4967
Congregational Library Archives
0.62 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes)
The First Congregational Church in Georgetown was originally established in 1731 as Rowley West Parish. When the town of Georgetown was incorporated in 1838, the Rowley West Parish was renamed to the First Congregational Church of Georgetown. The collection includes meeting minutes, financial records and valuable vital records.
Braman, Isaac, 1770-1858
First Congregational Church (Georgetown, Mass.)
Second Parish (Rowley, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Loaned to the Congregational Library & Archives, August 2011, by the First Congregational Church in Georgetown, Mass; no accession number.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Historical Note
The First Congregational Church in Georgetown was originally established in 1731 as the Rowley West Parish, also known as the Second Parish. Prior to the church's founding, parishioners had to travel a significant distance to worship in Rowley or neighboring Byfield. By 1768 the parish had outgrown its original meeting house and a new building was built. This meeting house, later known as Old South Church, was constructed on the corners of East Main and Elm Streets in 1769.
When the town of Georgetown was incorporated in 1838, the Rowley West Parish was renamed to the First Congregational Church of Georgetown. The third and final meeting house was constructed in 1874 along Andover Street. In 1908, the church merged with the Orthodox Memorial Church. In 1961, the church voted to become a member of the United Church of Christ. The First Congregational Church in Georgetown continues to serve the community today.
Scope and Contents
The First Congregational Church records of Georgetown, Mass. document the activities and history of the church organization and its members. The documents include meeting and committee minutes, financial records, membership records, vital records, and sermon manuscripts.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in chronological order by start date.
Technical Requirements
To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari 5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.
Baptism and church membership.; Baptismal records.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Funeral sermons.; Marriage records.; Necrologies.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Oaths.; Registers of births, etc.; Sermons, American -- 19th century.; Sermons, American -- Early works to 1800.; Tax remission.; First Congregational Church (Georgetown, Mass.); Georgetown (Mass.) -- Church history.; Second Parish (Rowley, Mass.)
- Parish records, 1731 1814; 1731-1814 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  Digital Copies
  These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
  Scope and Contents
  This volume contains records of the officers' meetings for the West Parish in Rowley, concerning the oversight of the property and finances. It includes records of parish votes for the officers' and ministers' salaries, various committee assignments, pew subscriptions, and upkeep of the meetinghouse.
- Account book of births, 1731 1786; 1731-1786 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  Unlike most similar records of the time, this volume records actual birth (rather than baptismal) dates, along with the names of the parents and locations of baptisms.
- Account book of deaths, 1731 1854; 1731-1854 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  This volume contains a list of the members and children of members who passed away. Each entry includes the date and approximate age, as well as parents for those who died young.
- Church records, 1732 1855; 1732-1855 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online. Transcriptions of this record are also available and can be viewed alongside the digital images.
  This volume primarily contains membership records for the Second Parish Church in Rowley. These include admissions, dismissions, baptisms, and disciplinary cases. There is also a copy of the covenant signed by the founding members.
- Church covenant, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  This shortened version of the original church covenant was likely used to admit new members. It includes references to the "Westminster Assembly's catechism" and the "sacraments of the New Testament"
- Sermons preached by Rev. Isaac Braman at Byfield, 1759 1781; 1759-1781 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  These sermons were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
  This folder contains manuscript sermons written and preached by Rev. Isaac Braman.
  List of Sermons
  Proverbs 30:12 – "There is a generation that are pure in their own eyes, yet is not washed from their filthiness."
  Proverbs 13:9 – "The light of the righteous rejoiceth: But the Lamp of the wicked shall be put out."
  Proverbs 1:33 – "But whoso hearkeneth unto me, shall dwell safely, shall be quiet from fear of evil."
  Philippians 2:9-11 – "Wherefore God hath highly exalted him, given him a name which is above every name: that at the name of Jesus every knee should bow…"
  Proverbs 23:17-18 – "Let not thine heart envy Sinners: but be thou in the fear of the Lord all the day long. For surely there is an End, thine expectation shall not be cut off."
  Proverbs 19:8 – "He that getteth wisdom, loveth his own Soul: he that keepeth understanding shall find good."
  Proverbs 17:16 – "Wherefore is there a price in the hand of a Fool to get wisdom, seeing he hath no heart to it."
  Philippians 3:13-14 – "Brethren, I count not my self to have apprehended: but this one think I do, forgetting those things which are behind, reaching forth unto those things which are before, I press toward the mark for the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus."
  2 Peter 3:14 – "Wherefore, beloved, seeing that ye look for such things, be diligent that ye may be found of him in peace, without spot, blameless."
  2 Peter 1:14 – "Knowing that shortly I must put off this my Tabernacle even as our Lord Jesus Christ hat shewed me."
  1 Peter 4:3-4 – "For the time past of our lives may suffice us to have wrought the will of the gentiles, when we walked in lasciviousness, lusts, excess of wine, revellings, banquetings, abominable idolatries…"
  Supplement – it is unclear which sermon this was supplemental to.
- Pulpit supply diary, 1787 1819; 1787-1819 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  This volume is a record of the guest preachers at both Second Parish Rowley and Byfield, and the scriptures on which they preached. It also includes a section of vital statistics for Second Parish from ca. 1706 to ca. 1812.
- Sermons preached by Rev. Isaac Braman at Georgetown, 1794 1836; 1794-1836 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  John 4:24 – "God is a Spirit, they that worship him must worship in Spirit in truth."
  Psalms 26:8 – "Lord, I have loved the habitation of thy house, and the place where thine honor dwelleth."
  Hebrews 11:4 – "By faith Abel offered to God a more excellent sacrifice than Cain."
  Zechariah 4:7 – "Who art thou, O great mountain? Before Zerubbabel thou shalt become a plain, he shall bring forth the headstone thereof with shouting, crying, Grace, grace unto it."
  Job 19:21 – "Have pity upon me, have pity upon me, O ye my friends, for the hand of God hath touched me."
- Marriage records, 1797 1854; 1797-1854 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  This brief volume contains a list of marriages performed by Rev. Isaac Braman during his tenure. Most were performed at the church in Georgetown, and one or both participants were members there. Braman also recorded the fees he was paid for each ceremony, usually two or three dollars.
- Parish financial records, 1799 1866; 1799-1866 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  The treasurers' ledger records the income and expenses of the parish, including taxes collected by assessors, staff salaries, fees for various services to the church, and the purchase of supplies such as firewood.
- Funeral sermon for Amos Spofford and Abigail Palmer, 1805 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  This sermon was digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
  "A sermon delivered at Rowley by the Rev. Isaac Braman, Dec. 29th 1805, occasioned by the death of Dr. Amos Spofford and Miss Abigail Palmer" on 2 Samuel 11:26 and Matthew 9:18. Spofford was a local physician and farmer, as well as one of the original members of the Massachusetts Medical Society. Abigail was the 14-year-old daughter of John and Martha Palmer.